地球脉动 Ⅲ
第七集
翻译：弥禾
吸鼻
SNUFFLING
尼泊尔索拉哈。
Sauraha, Nepal.
鼻塞和咕噜声
SNUFFLES AND GRUNTS
喇叭蜂鸣声
HORN BEEPS
狗呜咽声
DOG WHIMPERS
这头犀牛并没有迷路。
This rhino is not lost.
他正在去寻找食物的路上。
He is on his way to find food.
为了得到它，他必须穿越一个新的陌生世界。
To get it, he must travel through a new and alien world.
这头犀牛在其一生中
This rhino in his lifetime
比他的前几代人经历了更多的变化。
has seen more changes than any of his previous generations.
在全球范围内，
Across the globe,
现在各种动物都在争夺
animals of all kinds are now contending
一个新的优势物种...
with one newly dominant species...
...我们。
...us.
喇叭声、警报声
HORN BEEPS, SIREN WAILS
像许多野生动物一样，他必须学习
Like so many wild creatures, he's had to learn
如何在人类世界中生存。
how to live in the human world.
人类
解说
大卫·爱登堡
一些动物
Some animals
改变了他们的行为
have changed their behaviour
充分利用我们之间的生活。
to make the most out of living amongst us.
这些长尾猕猴生活在巴厘岛。
These long-tailed macaques live in Bali.
他们发展了新的兴趣
They have developed new interests
由人类访客带来。
brought by human visitors.
每天早上，部队都会前往一座建筑物
Every morning, the troop heads for a building
在他们领土的中心。
in the centre of their territory.
乌鲁瓦图寺。
Uluwatu Temple.
猕猴尖叫
MACAQUES SCREECH
每天都有成群结队的游客来到这里。
Tourists come here every day - in crowds.
所以寺庙里充满了机会......
So the temple grounds are full of opportunities...
...如果您知道去哪里寻找。
...if you know where to look.
女人喘息
WOMAN GASPS
帽子的供应源源不断……
There is a constant supply of hats...
...还有太阳镜。
...and sunglasses.
如果你已经掌握了惊喜的元素......
And if you've mastered the element of surprise...
……很容易得到它们。
...it's easy to get them.
但这个收获不是用来吃的。
But this harvest is not for eating.
是为了讨价还价。
It's for bargaining.
看起来像是公平交易。
Seems like a fair trade.
但还有更大的回报
But there are greater rewards to be had
对于那些知道如何获得它们的人。
for those who know how to get them.
相机快门点击
CAMERA SHUTTERS CLICK
而这个老男人似乎正在做……
And this old male appears to be doing...
...很好。
...very well.
他和这支队伍中的其他长老
He and the other elders in this troop
既有经验又有知识。
have both experience and knowledge.
他们在寺庙里工作了十多年，
They've been working the temple for over ten years,
现在专注于大事......
and now concentrate on the big stuff...
...人类离不开的东西。
...things that human beings just can't do without.
女人喘息
WOMAN GASPS
没有人愿意只穿一只鞋走路回家。
No-one wants to walk home with just one shoe.
女人喘息
WOMAN GASPS
这些老男孩已经等不及了
And these old boys can't wait
让他们掌握最新的技术。
to get their hands on the latest tech.
她感叹道
SHE EXCLAIMS
他们发现我们根本无法生存
They've worked out that we simply can't survive
没有我们的手机...
without our phones...
...或者我们的钱包。
...or our wallets.
女人惊呼
WOMAN EXCLAIMS
猕猴尖叫声
MACAQUE SCREECHES
女人喘息
WOMAN GASPS
年长的男性都明白
The older males understand
年轻人还没有学到的东西......
something the youngsters have yet to learn...
...交易的艺术。
...the art of the deal.
一根香蕉？
A banana?
你怎么敢！
How dare you!
猕猴尖叫声
MACAQUE SCREECHES
一块巧克力？
A bar of chocolate?
这样更好。
That's better.
真正的技巧在于谈判。
The real skill is in the negotiations.
猕猴正在玩我们自己的游戏。
The macaques are playing us at our own game.
他们要求...
They demand...
...无论他们想要什么。
...whatever they want.
人类已经传播到地球的每一个角落。
Humanity has spread to every corner of the globe.
我们已经成为自然的力量。
We have become a force of nature.
我们已经改变了80%的土地表面。
We have altered 80% of the land's surface.
现在有八十亿人生活在这个星球上......
Eight billion people now live on this planet...
...我们正在改变我们周围的世界
...and we are changing the world around us
以这样的速度...
at such speed...
...对于动物来说，挑战是跟上。
...that, for animals, the challenge is to keep up.
纽约市。
New York City.
蚂蚁。
Ants.
人们认为这个特殊的物种已经到达这里
This particular species is thought to have arrived here
与第一批欧洲定居者一起。
with the first European settlers.
他们现在被称为路面蚂蚁
They are now known as pavement ants
因为他们几乎只住在我们的城镇里。
because they live almost exclusively in our towns and cities.
他们因垃圾食品而蓬勃发展。
And they're thriving because of junk food.
而在百老汇大街这里，
And here on Broadway Avenue,
有很多。
there's a lot of it.
这是每只路面蚂蚁所渴望的。
This is what every pavement ant desires.
并且为了得到它...
And to get it...
...蚂蚁利用城市的数千英里
...the ants use the city's thousands of miles
的地下隧道。
of underground tunnels.
这名侦察兵正在逼近目标。
This scout is closing in on its target.
但与他们共享人行道的动物
But the animals with which they share the pavement
是其体重的4000万倍...
are 40 million times their weight...
脚步跺脚
FOOTSTEPS STOMP
……所以最好留在夹缝中。
...so it's best to stay in the cracks.
大奖！
Jackpot!
一座肉山。
A meat mountain.
对于一只蚂蚁来说，这项工作太大了。
This is too big a job for just one ant.
这位工人是女性，
This worker is female,
就像所有的蚁群一样，
as they are in all ant colonies,
她会留下一条信息素的痕迹来标记一条路径。
and she leaves a trail of pheromones to mark a path.
她和她遇到的每一个姐妹都有交流
She communicates with every sister she meets
当她回到巢穴时，
as she returns to the nest,
街上的消息传得很快。
and news on the street spreads fast.
这种超加工肉
This ultra-processed meat
和他们原来的食物有很大不同。
is very different from their original food.
但他们的消化系统是他们成功的关键。
But their digestive system is the key to their success.
它能够跟得上路
It's able to keep up with the way
人类不断改变饮食习惯。
humans constantly change their diet.
如今，他们吃的绝大多数东西
Nowadays, the vast majority of what they eat
来自人类食物。
comes from human food.
仅在百老汇，
On Broadway alone,
路面蚂蚁吃等量的食物
pavement ants eat the equivalent
每年生产 60,000 只热狗，数量惊人。
of a staggering 60,000 hot dogs every year.
一个热狗的热量
The calories in a single hot dog
可以推动增长
could fuel the growth
整个蚁群一个月......
of the entire ant colony for a month...
...如果他们能把它带回巢就好了。
...if only they can get it back to the nest.
但这种缓慢的工作使他们变得脆弱。
But this slow work makes them vulnerable.
鸽子咕咕
PIGEON COOS
他们并不是唯一偏爱快餐的人。
They aren't the only ones partial to fast food.
这是一场将奖品带回家的竞赛。
It's a race to get their prize home.
可能会有损失...
There may be losses...
......但整个殖民地现在将会蓬勃发展。
...but the colony as a whole will now thrive.
事实上，路面蚂蚁在这里非常成功
In fact, pavement ants are so successful here
他们的人数比纽约人多 1,000 比 1。
that they outnumber human New Yorkers 1,000 to 1.
鸽子首席运营官
PIGEONS COO
但人类世界的成功可能更难
But success in the human world can be harder to achieve
如果你的声誉领先于你。
if your reputation precedes you.
在印度这里，
Here in India,
这条眼镜蛇正直奔一个村庄。
this cobra is heading directly for a village.
它已经嗅到了猎物的气味。
It has detected the scent of prey.
近两米长，
Nearly two metres long,
它一口就有足够的毒液
it has enough venom in a single bite
杀死十个人。
to kill ten people.
蛇咬伤是罪魁祸首
Snake bites are responsible
每年造成近 60,000 人死亡
for nearly 60,000 deaths a year
仅在印度。
in India alone.
他们如此默默地旅行
They travel so silently
他们的存在常常未被发现。
that their presence is often undetected.
而当他们狩猎时...
And when they are hunting...
……没有他们不会去的地方。
...there is no place they won't go.
一只蟾蜍。
A toad.
它分叉的舌头的每一个尖端
Each tip of its forked tongue
收集猎物的化学信号
collects chemical signals from the prey
并有助于揭示其立场。
and helps to reveal its position.
但近距离...
But up close...
眼镜蛇嘶嘶声
COBRA HISSES
...蛇依靠运动
...the snake relies on movement
来精确定位猎物。
to precisely locate its prey.
蟾蜍必须选择逃跑的时机。
The toad must pick its moment to escape.
每次接触地面的时候...
Every time it touches the ground...
...蟾蜍留下气味。
...the toad leaves behind a scent.
它可以隐藏...
It can hide...
……但这条踪迹会把蛇引向那里。
...but the trail will lead the snake to it.
这些眼镜蛇不只是在这里狩猎。
These cobras don't just hunt here.
他们住在这里。
They live here.
他们找到了印度教村民尊敬他们的家
They have found a home where the Hindu villagers revere them
并认为他们是半神。
and consider them to be demigods.
值得注意的是，科学家认为这种耐受性
Remarkably, scientists believe that this tolerance
导致了蛇行为的改变。
has led to a change in the snakes' behaviour.
他们移动得更慢
They move more slowly
如果受到干扰，则不太可能发起攻击。
and are less likely to strike if disturbed.
地球上最可怕的动物之一
One of the most feared animals on the planet
已经找到了一个可以接受他们的地方
has found a place where they are accepted
并且可以与人类共存。
and can coexist with human beings.
但对于生活在人类世界的许多动物来说，
But for many animals living in the human world,
保持低调是值得的。
it pays to keep a low profile.
在澳大利亚墨尔本这里，
Here in Melbourne, Australia,
有一种生物已经完善了伪装艺术。
one creature has perfected the art of camouflage.
一只蛙口小鸡。
A frogmouth chick.
它的父亲白天帮忙把它藏起来。
Its father helps to hide it during the day.
小鸡的叫声
CHICK SQUAWKS
它们是夜行性鸟类，
They are nocturnal birds,
随着白天变成夜晚，
and as day turns to night,
它的父母从阴影中走出来
its parents come out of the shadows
获得城市生活的回报。
to reap the rewards of urban living.
城市灯光创造
The city lights create
狩猎条件优越。
excellent conditions for hunting.
城市里的每个夜晚
Every night in the city
如同满月时一样明亮。
is as bright as when there is a full moon.
鸟叫声
BIRD SQUAWKS
所以城市蛙口经常...
So city frogmouths often...
……他们的嘴都塞满了。
...have their mouths full.
他成长得很快，今天他不会坐以待毙。
He's growing fast, and today he just won't sit still.
狗叫声
DOG BARKS
现在他已经暴露了他的存在。
And now he has revealed his presence.
蛙口行为的第一条规则是
The first rule of frogmouth behaviour is
白天不要动。
don't move in the day.
但这是蛙口一生中的一次
But this is the one time in a frogmouth's life
当想要飞翔的冲动根本无法抑制的时候。
when the urge to fly simply cannot be suppressed.
狗裤
DOG PANTS
喙的声音、狗的叫声
BEAK CLICKS, DOG BARKS
但他还没有准备好离开家。
But he's not ready to leave home just yet.
晚上来...
Come night-time...
……他又饿了。
...he's hungry again.
他已经完全清醒了……
He is wide awake...
...并想从他离开的地方开始。
...and wants to take off where he left off.
但他却受到了不必要的关注
But he's getting unwanted attention,
这次他的父母不在附近保护他。
and this time his parent is not nearby to protect him.
人类带着宠物，
Humans bring pets,
澳大利亚的猫每天杀死一百万只鸟。
and cats in Australia kill a million birds a day.
领铃叮当响
COLLAR BELL TINKLES
他的第一次正确飞行。
His first proper flight.
但除非他能找到一个安全的栖息地
But unless he can find a safe place to roost,
他仍然处于危险之中。
he is still in peril.
做好了。
Made it.
但如果他要像大人一样在城市里生存，
But if he is to survive in the city, like the adults,
他必须学会如何融入。
he'll have to learn how to blend in.
有些动物就是这么大胆
Some animals are so bold
他们甚至不想隐藏。
that they don't even try to hide.
在建筑群中看到大型掠食者是罕见的景象。
To see a large predator in the built-up world is a rare sight.
在北美的太浩湖，
And here in Lake Tahoe, in North America,
这些黑熊特别大……
these black bears are particularly big...
……他们正前往市中心。
...and they're heading right to the centre of town.
熊咀嚼物
BEAR CHOMPS
冬天即将来临，
Winter is approaching,
这些熊需要增加尽可能多的体重
and these bears need to put on as much weight as possible
在雪到来之前。
before the snow arrives.
这是一个饱餐一顿的好地方。
This is a great place to gorge.
喇叭声
HORN BLARES
现在是熊国。
It's now bear country.
栅栏吱吱作响
FENCE CREAKS
何必为了一顿饭而苦苦挣扎……
Why struggle for a meal...
...当你可以过马路时...
...when you can cross the street...
……外卖？
...for a takeaway?
这里有这么多食物
There's so much food here
有些熊重 50%
that some of the bears are 50% heavier
比他们的乡下表兄弟。
than their country cousins.
但为什么停在这里呢？
But why stop here?
有些熊只是想在里面吃饭。
Some bears just want to dine in.
女人喘息
WOMAN GASPS
少数幸运者能够从人类世界轻松获得一顿美餐。
A lucky few are able to get an easy meal from the human world.
但是当我们冒险到自然世界寻找食物时......
But when WE venture to the natural world in search of food...
……收获的规模不同。
...the harvest is on a different scale.
短短四十年的时间，
In just four decades,
捕鱼使鱼类数量减少了一半...
fishing reduced fish populations by half...
...给海洋掠食者带来了很大的问题
...and created great problems for the ocean predators
曾经有过这样的食物。
that once had such food to themselves.
船的号角吹响
SHIP'S HORN BLOWS
在温哥华岛海岸附近，
Off the coast of Vancouver Island,
座头鲸栖息于水域
humpback whales inhabit waters
那里的鲱鱼被过度捕捞。
where herring have been overfished.
然而，座头鲸以其聪明才智而闻名。
Humpbacks, however, are renowned for their ingenuity.
12年前，一位名叫Conger的成年男性
12 years ago, an adult male called Conger
采用了全新的喂养方式。
adopted a totally new way of feeding.
当水中鱼的密度较低时，
When the density of fish in the water is low,
鸟儿们潜入水中捕捉它们......
and birds are diving to catch them...
...座头鲸张开嘴
...the humpback opens its mouth
并创造一个被鱼误认为庇护所的空间。
and creates a space that the fish mistake for shelter.
鱼儿游在...
The fish swim in...
……陷阱就关闭了。
...and the trap is closed.
海康格鲸是第一头被发现这样做的座头鲸。
Conger was the first humpback whale to be seen doing this.
现在该地区有 30 头鲸鱼使用同样的技术。
Now 30 whales in the area use this same technique.
这里的座头鲸数量正在增长，
The population of humpbacks here is growing,
你可能认为这会
and you might think that this would
进一步减少鱼类资源，
reduce fish stocks even more,
但人们认为令人惊讶的事情正在发生。
but something surprising is thought to be happening.
这些微小的浮游植物是食物链的基础
These tiny phytoplankton are the basis of the food chain
并且需要重要的成分才能生长。
and need a vital ingredient to grow.
铁。
Iron.
鲸鱼的粪便富含铁...
Whale faeces are rich in iron...
...大鲸鱼大量生产它...
...and great whales produce it in enormous quantities...
...所以浮游植物繁盛，鲱鱼以它为食。
...so the phytoplankton flourishes, and herring feed on it.
事实上，鲸鱼的粪便
Whale faeces, in fact,
正在帮助恢复整个生态系统。
are helping to restore the whole ecosystem.
鲱鱼吸引海鸟，
The herring attract seabirds,
潜水的鸟从下面攻击它们，
diving birds attack them from beneath,
海鸥和海鸥从上面俯冲到它们身上。
and gulls and shearwaters dive on them from above.
即使是秃鹰也能从这场丰盛的盛宴中受益。
Even bald eagles benefit from this rich feast.
令人惊讶的是，尽管康格鲸和所有其他鲸鱼
Astonishingly, even though Conger and all the other whales
正在大口吃鱼，
are feasting on fish,
他们在海洋施肥方面的作用是如此有影响力
their role in fertilising the ocean is so influential
这里的鲱鱼数量实际上预计会增加。
that herring numbers here are actually predicted to increase.
以及它们在恢复环境活力方面发挥的作用......
And the role they play in rejuvenating the environment...
......对人类世界产生更大的影响。
...is having an even greater impact on the human world.
繁盛的浮游生物也收集碳
The flourishing plankton also collects carbon
从大气中，就像树一样......
from the atmosphere, just as trees do...
...如此之多以至于每头鲸鱼
...so much so that each great whale
与拥有 30,000 棵树的森林具有相同的影响。
has the same impact as a forest of 30,000 trees.
我们的大鲸鱼曾经被猎杀......
Our great whales were once hunted...
...如果它们恢复到捕鲸前的数量，
...and if they return to their pre-whaling numbers,
估计这相当于种草了
it's estimated that this would be equivalent to planting
超过300亿棵树。
over 30 billion trees.
鲸鱼现在被认为对人类有益。
Whales are now being recognised as benefiting humanity.
但对于大多数大型动物来说
But for most large animals,
与人类的竞争会带来冲突。
competition with humans brings conflict.
这头六吨重的非洲公象正处于鼎盛时期。
This six-tonne African bull elephant is in his prime.
大象咕噜声
ELEPHANT GRUNTS
为了获得女性赢得战斗的最佳机会，
To stand the best chance of winning fights for females,
他需要变得很大。
he needs to be big.
他能闻到附近有营养丰富的食物的味道。
He can smell highly nutritious food is near.
但跨越界限才能到达
But crossing the boundary to reach it
这是一次危险的旅程。
is a dangerous journey.
他必须等待黑暗的掩护。
He must wait for the cover of darkness.
火爆裂纹
FIRE CRACKLES
这些肯尼亚农民正在为即将到来的夜晚做准备。
These Kenyan farmers are preparing for the night ahead.
他们必须每天晚上看守他们的庄稼
They have had to guard their crops every night
过去两个月。
for the last two months.
距离收获只剩两天了，
With only two days until harvest,
这是一个关键时刻。
this is a critical time.
男人喊叫
MAN SHOUTS
在一个晚上，
In a single night,
一头公象可以毁掉整个庄稼
a bull elephant can destroy the entire crops
由十个农民生产。
produced by ten farmers.
喊叫
SHOUTING
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT ROARS
男人喊叫
MAN SHOUTS
但他冒着巨大的风险。
But he's taking a huge risk.
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT ROARS
喊叫
SHOUTING
大象的尖叫声
ELEPHANT SCREECHES
喊叫
SHOUTING
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT ROARS
大象喇叭
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT ROARS
他的身高是人类的两倍...
He's twice the height of a man...
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT ROARS
……他不会轻易退缩。
...and he won't back down easily.
喊叫
SHOUTING
人类与野生动物的冲突日复一日地发生。
This human-wildlife conflict happens night after night.
每年，它都会夺走生命
And each year, it takes the lives
仅在肯尼亚就有多达 200 头大象和 20 个人。
of up to 200 elephants and 20 people in Kenya alone.
低沉的隆隆声
LOW RUMBLING
这种对峙可能是致命的。
This standoff is potentially lethal.
农民们不得不打电话求助
The farmers have had to call for help
来自经验丰富的护林员团队。
from a team of highly experienced rangers.
虽然他们全副武装，
Although they're armed,
他们的任务是将大象赶出田野
their task is to drive the elephant out of the field
而不伤害它。
without harming it.
但公牛决心...
But the bull is determined...
大象喇叭
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
……坚守阵地。
...to hold ground.
低沉的隆隆声
LOW RUMBLING
护林员将不得不靠近......
The rangers will have to get closer...
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT ROARS
...徒步。
...on foot.
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT GROWLS
低沉的隆隆声
LOW RUMBLING
护林员必须采取...爆竹爆炸声
The rangers have to resort... FIRECRACKER BANGS
大象咆哮......鞭炮声。
ELEPHANT GROWLS ...to firecrackers.
鞭炮声、大象吼声
FIRECRACKER BANGS, ELEPHANT ROARS
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT GROWLS
公牛被赶出了这片土地......
The bull is driven from this field...
大象咆哮
ELEPHANT GROWLS
……然后撤退到灌木丛深处。
...and retreats deep into the bush.
对于这头公牛来说幸运的是，
Fortunately for this bull,
战斗已经和平解决。
the battle has been resolved peacefully.
诸如此类的努力减少了大象被杀的情况，
And efforts like these are seeing fewer elephants killed,
肯尼亚的人口又开始增加。
and their population in Kenya is starting to rise again.
但与野生动物发生冲突
But conflict with wildlife
现在正在以更大的规模发生
is now occurring on a far greater scale
作为结果
as a consequence
我们正在改变世界气候的方式。
of the way we are changing the world's climate.
一些干旱地区
Some arid regions
现在正在经历异常高的降雨量。
are now experiencing unusually high rainfall.
这对农作物生长有好处
And that is good for growing crops
这里是非洲东北部。
here in northeastern Africa.
但这也是完美的条件
But it's also the perfect conditions
对于一种特定的昆虫。
for one particular insect.
沙漠蝗虫。
Desert locusts.
它们通常是独居动物，
They're normally solitary creatures,
但大量地从沙子里冒出来
but emerging from the sand in great numbers
引发剧烈的身体变化。
triggers a dramatic physical change.
它们变成鲜艳的黄色
They turn a vivid yellow
并变得高度社交。
and become highly social.
他们在一起就是一支不可阻挡的军队。
Together, they are an unstoppable army.
步行，他们每天可以走一英里。
On foot, they can cover a mile a day.
但他们只能以这种方式走这么远。
But they can only go so far in this way.
他们需要找到高度。
They need to find height.
在这里，他们开始了最后的转变。
Up here, they begin their final transformation.
通常，需要单个昆虫
Normally, it takes an individual insect
至少要一个月才能成为有翅膀的成年人……
at least a month to become a winged adult...
...但在他们的社会形式中，他们的发展速度加快。
...but in their social form, their development speeds up.
压制
SQUELCHING
现在他们所需要的只是让翅膀变硬。
Now all they need is for their wings to harden.
一旦升空，他们一天可以飞行 60 英里。
Once airborne, they can travel 60 miles in a day.
蜂群合并，成为瘟疫。
Swarms merge and they become a plague.
这其中包含了数十亿个人，
This one contains billions of individuals,
一天吃那么多
and eats as much in a day
相当于德国的全部人口。
as the entire population of Germany.
今天在非洲东北部，
Today in northeastern Africa,
由于气候变化...
as a consequence of climate change...
...毁灭性的蝗虫激增
...devastating surges of locusts
变得越来越频繁。
are becoming more frequent.
两个世界正在碰撞。
Two worlds are colliding.
人类无意中创造了这样的条件
Unintentionally, humanity has created exactly the conditions
导致该物种数量爆炸。
that cause this species to explode in numbers.
但另一群动物却看到了
But another group of animals has seen
更大幅度的上升
an even more dramatic rise
作为我们行动的结果。
as a consequence of OUR actions.
我们增加了一些物种的数量
We have increased the numbers of a few species
几乎是天文数字。
almost astronomically.
小鸡叽叽喳喳
CHICKS CHEEP
按重量计算，
By weight,
现在世界上70%的鸟类是鸡
70% of the world's birds are now chickens
或其他家禽。
or other domesticated fowl.
我们每年饲养 700 亿头农场动物......
We rear 70 billion farm animals each year...
猪咕噜声
PIG GRUNTS
……他们每个人都需要喂养。
...and every one of them needs feeding.
生产食物
Producing the food
对于如此数量的家养动物
for such numbers of domesticated animals
对自然世界产生着深远的影响。
is having a profound impact on the natural world.
鸡叫声
CHICKENS CLUCK
亚马逊雨林——
The Amazon rainforest -
是印度面积的两倍。
twice the size of India.
真是太丰富了，
It's so rich,
它包含了地球上十分之一的物种。
it contains one in every ten species on the planet.
这里是这只树懒和她十个月大的孩子的家。
And it's home to this sloth and her ten-month-old baby.
他出生在一个环境
He was born into an environment
几乎没有受到人类的影响。
virtually untouched by humanity.
电锯嗡嗡声
CHAINSAW BUZZES
但现在人类甚至也声称拥有这个空间。
But now human beings are claiming even this space.
年复一年，我们清理了超过 200 万公顷的土地
Year after year, we clear over two million hectares
亚马逊森林——
of the Amazon forest -
面积相当于威尔士那么大。
an area the size of Wales.
我们几乎使用了所有这些
And we use nearly all of it
为牛腾出更多空间...
to make more space for cattle...
...并种植大豆来喂养我们的牲畜。
...and to grow soya to feed our livestock.
如今，栖息地破坏是最大的问题
Today, habitat destruction is the biggest problem
我们为世界各地的野生动物创造了。
we have created for wildlife around the world.
树枝沙沙作响
BRANCHES RUSTLE
这只豪猪在火灾中幸存下来......
This porcupine has survived the fire...
……正在获救。
...and is being rescued.
它正在被迁移到原始森林。
It's being relocated to pristine forests.
这将是它的新家。
This will be its new home.
只有少数幸运的动物
Only a fortunate few animals
正在被给予这样的第二次机会。
are being given such a second chance.
健康的自然世界不仅对野生动物至关重要……
A healthy natural world is not only vital for wildlife...
...但为了我们自己的存在。
...but for our own very existence.
我们必须以某种方式找到纠正平衡的方法。
Somehow we must find ways to redress the balance.
目前，绝大多数农业用地，
Currently, the vast majority of agricultural land,
超过75%，
more than 75%,
用于饲养牲畜，
is used to raise livestock,
这是非常低效的。
and this is very inefficient.
有解决方案。
There are solutions.
一是考虑我们吃什么。
One is considering what we eat.
如果我们不再吃肉类和奶制品
If we shift away from eating meat and dairy
并转向植物性饮食，
and move towards a plant-based diet,
然后太阳的能量直接用于种植我们的食物。
then the sun's energy goes directly into growing our food.
因为这样效率更高
And because that's so much more efficient,
我们仍然可以生产足够的食物来养活我们，
we could still produce enough to feed us,
但这样做需要使用四分之一的土地。
but do so using a quarter of the land.
这可以腾出相当于美国那么大的面积，
This could free up an area the size of the United States,
中国、欧盟和澳大利亚联合...
China, the European Union and Australia combined...
...然后可以回归自然的空间。
...space that could then be given back to nature.
人类的创新也许能够
And human innovations may be able
为野生动物做更多的事情。
to do even more for wildlife.
高科技农场现在垂直种植植物，
High-tech farms now grow plants vertically,
产量是同一地区种植粮食的 350 倍。
yielding up to 350 times the food grown in the same area.
这是我们已有的众多解决方案之一，
This is one of many solutions we already have,
其他的肯定也即将出现。
and others are surely on the horizon.
寻找保护地球上所有生命的方法
To find ways to protect all life on Earth
意味着重新想象我们未来如何在这个星球上生活。
means reimagining how we live on this planet in the future.
人类的聪明才智，
Human ingenuity,
我们寻找解决方案的非凡能力，
our extraordinary ability to find solutions,
让我希望我们能做到。
gives me hope that we can.
这将是重大挑战
It will be the major challenge
为了这一代和下一代。
for this generation and the next.
拍摄影响
To film the impact
亚马逊雨林正在发生火灾，
that fires are having on the Amazon,
地球脉动 III 团队
the Planet Earth III team
加入了当地的志愿消防队。
joined a local volunteer fire brigade.
消防队正在响应补丁
The fire brigade are responding to a patch
正在燃烧的原始雨林。
of primary rainforest that is burning.
现在已经烧了两天了。
It's been burning for two days now.
很难知道我们会看到什么。
It's difficult to know what we're going to see.
火灾主要是非法纵火...
The fires are mainly lit illegally...
...为牛清理空间。
...to clear space for cattle.
真的很激烈
看看那边的火
我以前从未见过这样的事
来吧，用水泵
从远处做
把拐角处的火停下来
扑灭火灾是一项危险的工作。
Battling fires is dangerous work.
但消防员每天都会面对他们。
But the firefighters face them every day.
对于野生动物电影摄制组来说，
For the wildlife film crew,
这是一种全新的体验。
this is a totally new experience.
这些火灾可能是不可预测的。
And these fires can be unpredictable.
尼尔，别在那里呆太久。
Neil, don't spend long in there.
我们需要小心，这样火就不会烧到这里
现在的风很危险
我认为我们；我们得跑了
我知道时间流逝
哦！
Oh!
往这边跑
这很可怕
随着地面部队的撤退，
With the ground team retreating,
最安全的拍摄方式是使用无人机。
the safest way to carry on filming is with the drone.
我们失去了无人机吗？
我想阿比已经看到了。
Have we lost the drone? I think Abi has seen it.
阿比正在赶来的路上。
Abi is on her way.
阿比，你能确认你正在前往无人机的路上吗？
Can you confirm you're on your way to the drone, Abi?
无人机已经起火
男人喊叫
MAN SHOUTS
我有无人机
它在我们面前坠毁了
它着火了
无人机已损坏且无法修复。
The drone is damaged beyond repair.
别担心。
我是认真的。
Don't worry about it. I mean it.
别担心。
绝对没问题。
Don't worry about it. It's absolutely fine.
这不行。
这是。
没关系。
It's not OK. It is. It's OK.
是装备啊
我们有一个备用的。
It's equipment. We've got a spare.
最重要的是，我们都很安全。
没有人受伤。
The main thing is, we're all safe. No-one's hurt.
球队重新集结……
The team regroup...
...并决定远离火源
...and decide to move away from the heart of the fire
到它的边缘
to its fringes
寻找被火焰困住的动物。
to look for animals caught up in the flames.
有报道称树上有一只猴子，所以...
There's been reports of a monkey in the trees, so...
啊!
Ah!
他们说葡萄牙语
THEY SPEAK PORTUGUESE
问题是这里一路上都着火
The problem is, there's fires all the way along here,
以及一直在这里，所以...
as well as all along here, so...
很难知道这些野生动物会做什么
It's hard to know what all this wildlife is going to do
当他们的家被烧成这样的时候。
when their home is burnt up like this.
我不知道这些雨林动物的感受如何
I don't know what it's like for these rainforest animals
遭遇火灾。
to be experiencing a fire.
这对我来说太可怕了，所以...
It's horrific for me, so...
……我不知道这对他们来说意味着什么。
...I don't know what it is for them.
大火一直燃烧到深夜。
The fires burn into the night.
第二天，
The following day,
船员陪同消防员
the crew accompany the firefighters
灾后寻找动物的过程中。
in the search for animals in the aftermath.
天哪，里面全是火焰。
Oh, my God, there are flames all inside of it.
小白蚁...
Little termite...
我的天啊！
Oh, my God!
值得注意的是，一些动物幸存下来。
Remarkably, some animals have survived.
对我来说很痛苦
因为大自然是有生命的，就像我们一样
我们所拥有的一切，它也拥有
所以看到这样的森林很难过
受罚应该！但不应该这样对待
它一定很强壮
给我们力量
因为如果它变弱，我们就会感觉更弱
如果它倒下了，我们都会倒下
清理土地用于农业
Clearing land for farming
这并不是亚马逊独有的问题。
is not a problem unique to the Amazon.
农业现在占据了一半的可居住土地
Agriculture now takes up half of the habitable land
在这个星球上。
on the planet.
生产对自然世界影响较小的食品
To produce food with less impact on the natural world
需要新的方法。
requires new approaches.
这让野生动物电影摄制组来到了一个农场
And that led the wildlife film crew to a farm
在一个仓库里。
in a warehouse.
我们在市中心！
We're in the middle of the city!
我简直不敢相信有这么多食物
I can't believe so much food
竟然在这么小的空间里生长！
being grown in such a small space!
在距离亚马逊 6,000 英里的洛杉矶，
Here in Los Angeles, 6,000 miles from the Amazon,
这个农场是蓬勃发展的食品革命的一部分。
this farm is part of a burgeoning food revolution.
这是世界上生产力最高的农场，
This is the most productive farm in the world,
我们的目标是减少土地和资源的数量
and it's our goal to reduce the amount of land and resources
必须增长到最低限度。
necessary to grow down to the bare minimum.
我花了一段时间才明白，对于大自然来说，
It took a while to understand that, for nature,
农业用地
agricultural use of land
是人类主要的破坏性行为。
was the primary, like, destructive behaviour of humanity.
当我们扩大这种增长方式时，
As we expand this means of growing,
我非常希望这种方法最终能够
I'm very hopeful that this approach can ultimately
让大量土地回归自然
give a lot of land back to nature
并让生物多样性得以重建和繁荣。
and allow that biodiversity to re-establish and flourish.
这个农场不仅占用的空间更少......
Not only does this farm use less space...
...但它的用水量也减少了 90%，
...but it also uses 90% less water,
没有农药，
no pesticides,
并减少食物里程。
and cuts food miles.
这确实感觉像是一个很好的开始。
It does feel like a really good start.
像这样的想法可以减少我们在地球上的足迹，
Ideas like this can reduce our footprint on the planet,
给自然世界一个反弹的机会。
giving the natural world a chance to bounce back.
下次，
Next time,
奋战在前线拯救野生动物的英雄们。
the heroes on the frontline saving wildlife.
他们正在探索偏远的丛林......
They're exploring remote jungles...
...卧底抓捕罪犯...
...working undercover to catch criminals...
...并将濒临灭绝的生物引导到安全的地方。
...and leading endangered creatures to safety.
栖息地探索者让动物及其栖息地栩栩如生。
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
探索这个免费的互动并制作折纸动物。
Explore this free interactive and make origami animals.
去...
Go to...
...然后点击开放大学的链接。
...and follow the links to the Open University.
或者要订购免费印刷版，请访问网站
Or to order a free printed version, visit the website
或拨打屏幕上的号码。
or call the number on the screen.